♪Confessing to the moon in the rustling wind back then♪
♪จันทร์เคยแจ่มกระจ่าง♪
♪Like a boat being swallowed up among the cities♪
♪พลันแปรเป็นทะเลคลั่ง♪
♪Watching the flowers fall in unease, worries and troubles fill my mind♪
♪ตระหนกฟังเสียงบุปผาโรย♪
♪Am I going to where I want♪
♪ทุกที่ที่ไป♪
♪To stay or to leave, you decide♪
♪ด้วยการไปหรืออยู่ของเจ้า♪
♪Nations are different♪
♪ปฐพีกับแผ่นดินก็ต่างกัน♪
♪One without desire is one that is not alive♪
♪ฟ้าดินไร้ใจ♪
♪Looking at the sky side by side♪
♪ร่วมเคียงชมนภา♪
♪We've gotten closer with time♪
♪กาลเข้มข้นกว่าเวลา♪
♪One glance, the city of Chang'an is bare♪
♪มองผ่านปราดเดียว♪
♪Among the ridiculous people and things is me♪
♪ในเรื่องราวเหลวไหลของผู้คน♪
=Episode 17=
=ตอนที่ 17=
Yanzhi.
เยียนจือ
Hurry.
เร็วเข้า
Just run.
รีบหนี
How could I run away
ไม่มีเจ้า
without you?
ข้าจะหนีอย่างไร
I'll help you out.
ข้า ข้าช่วยท่าน
I'll hold him off.
รั้งใต้เท้าเอาไว้
I do not know any martial arts.
ข้าไม่มีวรยุทธ
I have a weak heart as well.
ทั้งยังมีโรคทุกข์ทางใจ
I will never be able to escape
ไม่มีเจ้า
without you.
ข้าจะหนีไปที่ใด
Xiu,
อาซิว
you will help me out,
เจ้าจะช่วยข้า
am I right?
ใช่หรือไม่
I'll show it to you again.
ข้าจะแสดงให้ท่านดูอีกครั้ง
There are seven underground chambers located under
ห้องใต้ดินจัตุรัสของสำนักหมากรุก
the square of the Chess of Generals Camp.
มีทั้งหมดเจ็ดห้อง
They're arranged according to the position of the Big Dipper.
จัดตำแหน่งตามดาวเหนือทั้งเจ็ด
There are two exits in total.
ทั้งหมดมีทางเข้าออกสองทาง
The exit of Alpha Ursae Majoris is connected to the woodshed.
ทางออกตำแหน่งเทียนซู เชื่อมกับห้องเก็บฟืน
You can leave the camp through the exit.
สามารถออกไปนอกค่ายได้
The exit of Eta Ursae Majoris is located at my room.
ทางออกตำแหน่งเหยากวง อยู่ที่ห้องของข้า
Ask Ziyuan to bring Prince Guang
ให้จื่อย่วนพากวงอ๋อง
and leave through the secret path of Alpha Ursae Majoris.
ออกไปตามทางลับตำแหน่งเทียนซู
As for you,
ส่วนท่าน
you can bring Qi Yan with you to the Eta Ursae Majoris exit.
พาฉีเยี่ยนไปที่ตำแหน่งเหยากวง
Remember,
หลบหลีกให้ดี
you must avoid triggering the traps.
อย่าได้ไปเปิดกลไกเข้า
This is the switch
นี่เป็นปุ่มกดระเบิด
to detonating the explosives.
สุดท้าย
Were you thinking of
ตอนนั้นที่ท่าน
using these traps against Qiu Ziliang
ซ่อมแซมกลไกพวกนี้
when you first
ก็คิดที่จะใช้มัน
built these traps?
เพื่อจัดการกับฉิวจื่อเหลียงแล้วงั้นหรือ
Yes.
ใช่
- Let's go! - Let's take a look.
ไป ไปดูกัน
What are you doing?
เจ้าคิดจะทำอะไร
Six,
เสี่ยวลิ่วจื่อ
come.
มา
Eat up.
กินให้เยอะหน่อยนะ
Say that again.
พูดอีกครั้งสิ
Yes, my lord.
ขอรับใต้เท้า
Yanzhi is Wang Yang's granddaughter.
เยียนจือคือบุตรีภรรยาหลักของหวังหยาง
Her surname is Wang.
แซ่หวัง
And her name is Ruoqing.
ชื่อ รั่วชิง
She stayed beside you
เพื่อแก้แค้น
because she wanted to avenge her family.
จึงมาอยู่ข้างกายท่านขอรับ
Now, she has joined hands with Han Yue
บัดนี้นางร่วมมือกับหานเยว่
and they've captured His Majesty.
จับฝ่าบาท
They plan to capture you as well.
พวกเขายังคิดจะจับท่านด้วย
My lord,
ใต้เท้า
please take a look.
โปรดดูสิ่งนี้สักหน่อยขอรับ
These are the intel
ข้างบนนี้คือสิ่งที่ข้าสืบค้น
that I've gathered.
มาอย่างละเอียด
My lord, please take a look.
ขอใต้เท้าตรวจดูด้วยขอรับ
Nine.
เสี่ยวจิ่วจื่อ
You better stay obedient.
ไม่เชื่อฟังใช่ไหม
This is interesting.
น่าสนใจ ๆ
Tell us!
ว่ามา
Who did you tip off just now?
เมื่อกี้เจ้าส่งข่าวให้ใคร
Han Ding?
หานติ้ง
You were actually in hiding all along?
เจ้าแฝงตัวอยู่ใกล้ ๆ ตลอดเวลา
Why didn't you appear earlier?
ทำไมไม่ออกมาให้เร็วกว่านี้ล่ะ
His Majesty told me
ฝ่าบาทเคยรับสั่งเอาไว้
not to show myself before I see the flare.
ถ้าไม่เห็นดอกไม้ไฟ ห้ามเผยตัวเด็ดขาด
But, His Majesty handed over the flare to me.
ฝ่าบาทมอบดอกไม้ไฟไว้ให้ข้า
Go now!
รีบไป
His Majesty is still inside the Chess of Generals Camp.
ฝ่าบาทยังอยู่ที่สำนักหมากรุก
Go and save him.
รีบไปช่วยพระองค์เร็ว
You have a fever.
เจ้าเป็นไข้หรือ
It's fine. It won't kill me.
ไม่เป็นไร ไม่ตายหรอก
Let's go.
ไป
Don't be afraid.
ไม่ต้องกลัวนะ
Where's Yanzhi?
เยียนจืออยู่ที่ไหน
My lord,
เรียนใต้เท้า
she's hiding under the secret chamber below the square.
นางอยู่ที่ด้านล่างของกลไกที่จัตุรัสขอรับ
Is there only one entrance to the secret chamber?
กลไกมีทางเข้าทางเดียวงั้นหรือ
My lord,
เรียนใต้เท้า
you're correct.
ใช่ขอรับ
My friend, since you're here,
ในเมื่อสหายเก่ามาถึงแล้ว
why don't you come down and have a drink with me?
ทำไมถึงไม่ลงมาดื่มกันสักจอกเล่า
I have the Morning Dew Wine.
สุราเลิศรสเจาลู่
It is the best of the best.
สิ่งสุดยอดใต้หล้า
Please.
เชิญ
Where is Yanzhi?
ข้าถามเจ้าหน่อย เยียนจือเล่า
What?
ทำไม
Are you afraid that the wine is poisoned?
กลัวว่าในเหล้าจะมีพิษใช่ไหม
It's been eight years.
แปดปีแล้ว
Qiu Ziliang,
ฉิวจื่อเหลียง
I'm here
วันนี้ที่ข้ามาที่นี่
to take your wretched life today.
ก็เพื่อมาเอาชีวิตต่ำช้าของเจ้า
Han Yue,
หานเยว่
Yanzhi is the reason I'm here today.
วันนี้ข้ามาเพื่อเยียนจือ
Call her out,
เจ้าเรียกนางออกมา
and I may leave you with a complete body.
ข้าจะให้เจ้าตายครบสามสิบสอง
Fine.
เอาสิ
You have to get through me first.
เช่นนั้นก็ผ่านด่านข้าไปก่อน
Qiu Ziliang,
ฉิวจื่อเหลียง
you have plenty of things waiting for you
ข้างล่างยังมีเรื่องสนุก
down below.
รอเจ้าอยู่อีกเยอะ
Follow me if you dare.
แน่จริงก็ตามข้าลงมาสิ
Hurry!
เร็ว
Call for the Shencai Army.
รีบไปเรียกทัพเสินไฉมา
As for the rest,
ส่วนคนอื่น ๆ
stay here and wait for Official Qiu's return.
ป้องกันใต้เท้าอยู่ที่นี่กับข้า
Hurry!
เร็วเข้า
Who's there?
ใครน่ะ
Move aside!
หลีกไป
Official Yan?
ใต้เท้าเหยียน
Where are you going?
จะไปไหนเหรอ
Under Eunuch Qiu's order,
ได้รับคำสั่งจากกงกง
we need to head to the Chess of Generals Camp.
โยกกำลังทหารมาที่สำนักหมากรุกขอรับ
Where's the Shencai Army?
ทัพเสินไฉทำไมยังมาไม่ถึงอีก
My lord,
เรียนใต้เท้า
I've relayed your command to them.
แจ้งคำสั่งไปแล้วขอรับ
Left Knight.
จั่วหม่า
Yan Xiu?
เหยียนซิว
Seems like you've recovered.
ดูเหมือนว่าเจ้าจะหายดีแล้วนะ
Since he has recovered,
เขาหายดีแล้ว
it's time for you to be in trouble.
เจ้าก็น่าจะมีปัญหาเสียแล้ว
Someone.
ตามคนมา
Take down both of them.
จับพวกเขาสองคนเอาไว้
Go!
เข้าไปสิ
Attack them!
ลุยเข้าไปให้หมด ๆ
Why are you standing there?
เหม่ออะไรอยู่ดี
Useless fools!
ตัวไร้ค่า
Don't move!
อย่าขยับ
Great.
ดีนี่
So,
พวกเจ้าแต่ละคน
are you guys going to betray Eunuch Qiu?
ล้วนทรยศกงกงกันทั้งนั้นใช่ไหม
Just wait until Eunuch Qiu is out.
รอให้กงกงออกมาจากที่นั่นเมื่อไร
I gave you one last chance before this.
ข้าเคยให้โอกาสกับเจ้าแล้ว
What?
ทำไม
You want me to be grateful to you
ข้ายังต้องขอบคุณเจ้า
when you've laid down another trap for me?
ที่วางกับดักข้าอีกหรือไง
You wouldn't have fallen for it
ถ้าหากเจ้าไม่ละโมบ
if you weren't greedy in the first place.
ก็จะไม่ตกหลุมพราง
I was being greedy?
ละโมบ
Let's go.
ไปเถอะ
Time to execute the next step.
ควรเดินหมากต่อไปแล้ว
Speaking of which,
ว่าไปแล้ว
it's my first time visiting this place.
ข้าเพิ่งมาที่นี่เป็นครั้งแรกเลยนะ
I need to take a good look at it.
จะต้องดูให้ดี ๆ หน่อย
Sure.
เอาสิ
You can take a good look at it.
เช่นนั้นเจ้าก็ดูให้ดี ๆ
His Majesty has to stab himself with a hairpin because of me.
ข้าทำให้ฝ่าบาทต้องใช้ปิ่นทำร้ายพระองค์เอง
That's why Han Yue was able to get his hands on him.
ทำให้พระองค์ตกอยู่ในมือของหานเยว่
By the way,
ใช่แล้ว
Han Yue is the military advisor of Zhenwu.
หานเยว่ก็คือกุนซือเจิ้นอู๋
His Majesty knew about that long ago.
เรื่องนี้ฝ่าบาททรงรู้นานแล้ว
His Majesty knew about that long ago?
ฝ่าบาททรงรู้นานแล้วหรือ
Back then, His Majesty was the one who had saved Han Yue.
ตอนนั้นฝ่าบาทเป็นคนช่วยหานเยว่ไว้
You can finally avenge your family.
ในที่สุดท่านก็แก้แค้นได้แล้ว
But, I don't want to kill Qi Yan.
แต่ข้าไม่อยากให้ฉีเยี่ยนตาย
I want him
ข้าอยากให้เขาพลิกคดี
to prove my grandfather's and my family's innocence
ให้ท่านปู่และตระกูลหวังของข้า
while he's still the emperor.
ด้วยตนเองขณะครองราชย์
You can do the same
หลังจากกวงอ๋องขึ้นครองราชย์
after Prince Guang's ascension.
ก็สามารถทำได้เหมือนกัน
When Qi Yan does it,
ฉีเยี่ยนทำ
he's admitting his mistake
คือการยอมรับความผิด
and atoning for his sin.
เป็นการไถ่โทษ
Only then, it'll be meaningful.
ถึงจะมีความหมาย
Prince Guang
ส่วนกวงอ๋อง
will never be able to achieve the same.
ไม่ได้
Is this why you betrayed Qiu Ziliang
นี่ก็คือเป้าหมายที่เจ้าทรยศฉิวจื่อเหลียง
and joined hands with Han Yue?
แล้วร่วมมือกับหานเยว่งั้นหรือ
Is your surname Wang?
เจ้าแซ่หวัง
Are you...
เจ้าคือ
I will never forget
ในตอนนั้นธนูดอกนั้นของพระองค์
the arrow that you've shot.
หม่อมฉันจดจำไปชั่วชีวิต
Are you the elder sister?
เจ้าคือคนผู้พี่คนนั้นเหรอ
I couldn't find you after the incident.
หลังจากนั้นข้าหาเจ้าไม่เจอ
So, you're actually still alive?
แต่เจ้ากลับยังมีชีวิตอยู่
You were looking for me?
ตามหาหม่อมฉัน
Why were you looking for me?
พระองค์ตามหาหม่อมฉันทำไม
Your Highness,
ฝ่าบาท
it's been quite some time.
ผ่านไปนานขนาดนี้แล้ว
Even if we find her,
ต่อให้พวกเราหาเจอ
we won't be able to save her in time.
คาดว่าก็ไม่น่าช่วยได้แล้วพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
Not everyone
ไม่ใช่ว่าทุกคน
is as lucky as Zheng Wu.
จะโชคดีเหมือนเจิ้งอู่นะพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
Your Highness,
ฝ่าบาท
you've done your best.
พระองค์พยายามเต็มที่แล้ว
No.
ไม่ได้
They...
พวกนาง
I'm sure they're still alive.
พวกนางจะต้องยังมีชีวิตอยู่แน่
And...
อีกอย่าง
I promised Master
ข้าเคยรับปากอาจารย์แล้ว
that I will protect his lineage.
จะต้องเหลือทายาทของพวกเขาเอาไว้
Let's give it another try, okay?
หาดูอีกทีดีไหม
All right.
พ่ะย่ะค่ะ
I believe that they're still alive.
ข้าเชื่อว่าพวกนางจะต้องยังมีชีวิตอยู่
General Han!
แม่ทัพหาน
Your Highness,
ฝ่าบาท
General Han is still alive.
แม่ทัพหานยังมีชีวิตอยู่พ่ะย่ะค่ะ
Back then, His Majesty and I
ตอนนั้นข้ากับฝ่าบาท
went to the mass grave.
ไปที่ป่าช้ารวม
Initially, we wanted to save
เดิมทีพวกเราจะไปช่วยเหลือ
the two granddaughters of Wang Yang.
หลานสาวทั้งสองของหวังหยาง
We didn't expect to see Han Yue lying down there.
คิดไม่ถึงว่าได้เจอหานเยว่
After that, His Majesty told me
ดังนั้นฝ่าบาทเลยให้ข้านำเขา
to send him to House 16.
ส่งกลับไปที่เรือนสิบหก
Prince Guang cured him.
กวงอ๋องรักษาเขาจนหาย
After that, he sent him back to Zhenwu.
แล้วก็ส่งกลับไปที่เจิ้นอู๋
So,
ดังนั้น
regarding the royal retainers of Zhenwu
ขุนนางเมืองเจิ้นอู๋
escorting Princess Ninghe to the Capital,
อารักขาท่านหญิงหนิงเหอกลับเมืองหลวง
does His Majesty know that it has something
ฝ่าบาทก็ทรงรู้ตั้งนานแล้ว
to do with Han Yue long ago?
ว่าเกี่ยวข้องกับหานเยว่
That's right.
ใช่แล้ว
His Majesty ordered me to do a private investigation on him.
ฝ่าบาทสั่งให้ข้าสืบค้นส่วนตัว
But, he told me not to act.
แต่อย่าใช้กำลังทหาร
Why?
เพราะเหตุใด
Han Yue treats him as his enemy,
หานเยว่เห็นพระองค์เป็นศัตรู
but, he was the one who had saved Han Yue in the first place.
แต่พระองค์เป็นคนช่วยหานเยว่ไว้
Isn't that dangerous?
แบบนี้อันตรายมากเลยนะ
It is dangerous,
ก็อันตราย
but, it is an opportunity as well.
แต่ก็เป็นโอกาสเหมือนกัน
What if Han Yue
ถ้าหากหานเยว่
was able to kill Qiu Ziliang?
สามารถสังหารฉิวจื่อเหลียงได้จริง ๆ ล่ะ
His Majesty ordered me to eliminate the four important pawns
กำจัดตัวหมากสี่ตัวสำคัญ
of the Chess of Generals Camp.
ที่จัดวางไว้ด้านนอกของสำนักหมากรุก
His goal was
เป้าหมายก็เพื่อ
to shift Qiu Ziliang's attention
ดึงความสนใจของฉิวจื่อเหลียง
to Zhenwu.
ให้มาอยู่ที่เจิ้นอู๋
With that opportunity, he can summon Li Deyun to the Capital.
แล้วก็ถือโอกาส เรียกตัวหลี่เต๋ออวิ้นกลับเมืองหลวง
His Majesty thought of summoning
ฝ่าบาทคิดถึงใต้เท้าหลี่เต๋ออวิ้น
Official Li Deyun since long ago?
ไว้ตั้งนานแล้ว
If so, why didn't he agree to it
เช่นนั้นก่อนหน้านี้ตอนที่กวงอ๋องบอก
when Prince Guang had made the same suggestion to him?
เหตุใดพระองค์จึงไม่ทรงรับปากล่ะ
So, His Majesty doesn't trust Prince Guang.
ฝ่าบาทไม่เชื่อในตัวกวงอ๋อง
It's nothing.
ไม่มีอะไร
I'm glad
เจ้ายังมีชีวิตอยู่
that you're alive.
ข้าดีใจยิ่งนัก
Have you ever regretted your actions?
ฝ่าบาทเคยสำนึกเสียใจหรือไม่
If I have a second chance,
ถ้าทำได้อีกครั้ง
I'll do the same thing.
ข้าก็ยังจะทำเช่นนี้
Very good.
ดีมาก
General Han is right.
แม่ทัพหานพูดถูกแล้ว
A person like you
คนอย่างฝ่าบาท
deserves to die.
ตายไม่สาสมความผิด
It was foolish of me
หวังให้ทรงสำนึกผิดแล้วแก้ไข
to think that you would change your ways.
ไม่มีทางเป็นไปได้สักนิด
Master,
อาจารย์
should I believe in her?
ข้าควรเชื่อนางหรือไม่
She's your eldest granddaughter indeed.
นางเป็นหลานสาวคนโตของท่านจริง ๆ หรือ
Master,
อาจารย์
I really want
ข้าอยากจะปกป้องทายาทของท่าน
to protect your lineage.
เอาไว้จริง ๆ
Don't worry.
วางใจเถอะ
His Majesty is confident in his plan.
ฝ่าบาทคาดเอาไว้อยู่แล้ว
Before I fell unconscious,
ก่อนข้าสลบไป
I heard Ziyuan said that she was going
จื่อย่วนบอกว่าจะสังหาร
to kill both His Majesty and Qiu Ziliang.
ฝ่าบาทกับฉิวจื่อเหลียง
His Majesty is in danger right now.
ตอนนี้ฝ่าบาทอยู่ในอันตราย
And Yanzhi.
แล้วก็เยียนจือ
Yanzhi is inside as well.
เยียนจือก็ยังอยู่ข้างในด้วย
But, Official Li Deyun
แต่ตอนนี้ใต้เท้าหลี่เต๋ออวิ้น
is on his way right now.
กำลังเดินทางมาแล้ว
His Majesty said
ฝ่าบาทรับสั่งไว้
that we mustn't act
ไม่มีสัญญาณจากพระองค์
without his instructions.
ห้ามลงมือโดยพลการ
If so,
เช่นนั้น
how about this?
เช่นนั้นแบบนี้
I'll sneak in.
ข้าจะแอบเข้าไป
You can wait for me outside.
เจ้ารอข้าอยู่ข้างนอกก็พอ
Do you have another flare?
เจ้ามีดอกไม้ไฟหรือไม่
But, you're sick.
แต่เจ้ายังป่วยอยู่
It's precisely because I'm sick
ก็เพราะว่าข้ายังป่วยอยู่
that Han Yue had let down his guard against me.
หานเยว่ถึงจะไม่ระแวงข้า
And I'm familiar
อีกอย่างข้าก็คุ้นชิน
with the Chess of Generals Camp's terrain.
กับพื้นที่ในสำนักหมากรุก
I know that there's a secret path
ข้ารู้ว่ามีทางลับอยู่หนึ่งทาง
which connects to the underground chambers.
สามารถตรงไปยังห้องใต้ดินได้
All right.
ได้
Be careful.
ระวังตัวด้วย
Cheng Ruoyu?
เฉิงรั่วอวี๋
How did you return here?
เจ้ากลับมาได้อย่างไร
I'm here to save you.
ข้ามาช่วยท่าน
But, you didn't need
แต่คิดไม่ถึง
my help at all.
ว่าท่านจะไม่ต้องการให้คนมาช่วย
You're actually in cahoots with Han Yue.
ท่านกับหานเยว่เป็นพวกเดียวกัน
Are you going to kill me?
เจ้าจะลงมือกับข้างั้นหรือ
Release His Majesty.
ปล่อยฝ่าบาทซะ
That's impossible.
ไม่มีทาง
I'll kill you then!
เช่นนั้นข้าจะฆ่าท่านซะ
Calm down.
อย่าวู่วาม
We can talk over this.
มีอะไรก็คุยกันดี ๆ
Kill me then.
เจ้าฆ่าสิ
Cheng Ruoyu,
เฉิงรั่วอวี๋
you won't be able to kill anyone.
เจ้าไม่ใช่คนที่จะฆ่าคนได้
Qiu Yanzhi,
ฉิวเยียนจือ
I'll say this again.
ข้าจะพูดอีกครั้ง
Release His Majesty.
ปล่อยฝ่าบาท
I'll say this again as well.
ข้าก็จะพูดอีกครั้งเช่นกัน
That's impossible.
ไม่มีทาง
You have no way to escape from me.
ดูสิว่าเจ้าจะหนีไปไหน
Qiu Ziliang,
ฉิวจื่อเหลียง
I've been waiting for this day
ข้ารอวันนี้
for a long time.
มานานแล้ว
What other tricks do you have in store?
ยังมีลูกไม้อะไรอีก
Reveal all of them.
งัดออกมาให้หมดสิ
Rosa rubus?
พุทธแย้มสรวล
I'll see how long you can withstand this.
ดูสิว่าเจ้าจะฝืนได้อีกนานแค่ไหน
Much longer than you think.
นานกว่าที่เจ้าจินตนาการไว้
If you guys kill His Majesty,
ถ้าหากพวกท่านสังหารฝ่าบาท
the world will be plunged into chaos.
แผ่นดินจะสับสนวุ่นวาย
In the end, the people will be the ones who suffer.
สุดท้ายผู้รับเคราะห์ก็มีแต่ชาวบ้าน
Yanzhi,
เยียนจือ
he's out of his mind.
เขาบ้าไปแล้ว
Are you going to join him?
ท่านก็จะบ้าไปกับเขางั้นหรือ
General Han will assist Prince Guang to ascend the throne.
แม่ทัพหาน จะช่วยให้กวงอ๋องขึ้นครองราชย์
Everything is under control.
ทุกอย่างอยู่ภายใต้การควบคุม
But, Prince Guang
แต่ว่ากวงอ๋อง
isn't willing to ascend the throne.
เขาไม่ได้ยินยอมนี่นา
He doesn't get to make the call here.
ไม่ได้ขึ้นอยู่ว่าเขาไม่ยอม
She has blind loyalty to the emperor.
คนผู้นี้ซื่อสัตย์ภักดี
She will ruin our plan
ปล่อยนางไว้
if we keep her alive.
มีแต่จะทำให้พวกเราเสียเรื่อง
Why don't we kill her?
ไม่สู้ฆ่านางเสีย
General Han.
แม่ทัพหาน
She grew up within the palace.
คนผู้นี้โตมาในวัง
Since young, she was taught
ที่ได้รับการสั่งสอนมาตั้งแต่เด็ก
how to protect the emperor.
ก็คือต้องปกป้องฝ่าบาท
She's similar to you in some ways.
ในบางมุมก็เหมือนกับท่าน
Even so, we mustn't keep her alive.
กระนั้นก็เก็บนางไว้ไม่ได้
Let's send her out of Heng'an City.
พวกเราส่งนางออกจากเหิงอันเถอะ
We should let her off the hook.
ไว้ชีวิตนางสักครั้ง
Back then,
ตอนนั้น
the heavens
สวรรค์
had let you off the hook as well.
ก็ไว้ชีวิตท่านเช่นกัน
Fine.
ได้
I'll leave her to you.
ยกนางให้ท่านจัดการ
I'll force Qiu Ziliang to hand over his authority over the military.
ข้าจะไปหาฉิวจื่อเหลียง ให้มอบอำนาจทางทหารออกมา
Yanzhi,
เยียนจือ
please don't kill His Majesty.
ข้าขอร้องท่านอย่าฆ่าฝ่าบาทนะ
He isn't a villain.
พระองค์ไม่ใช่คนเลว
He did everything
เรื่องที่พระองค์ทำไปทั้งหมด
because he was forced by Qiu Ziliang.
ล้วนแต่เป็นเพราะฉิวจื่อเหลียงบีบบังคับ
He had saved many people as well.
พระองค์เคยช่วยคนไว้มากมาย
Some mistakes
ความผิดบางอย่าง
can never be forgiven
เมื่อทำผิดไปแล้ว
once they are committed.
ไม่อาจให้อภัยได้
Cheng Ruoyu,
เฉิงรั่วอวี๋
you weren't there during the Morning Dew Rebellion.
เมื่อตอนเหตุการณ์กบฏเจาลู่เจ้าไม่อยู่
You don't understand what it feels like
คนที่ไม่เคยประสบ
when you haven't experienced that by yourself.
ไม่รู้หรอกว่ารสชาติเป็นอย่างไร
Can you imagine how hard it is
เจ้าคิดว่าเจิ้งอู่
for Zheng Wu
เข้าไปอยู่ในหน่วยอาภรณ์ม่วง
to stay within the Violet Bureau?
ด้วยเจตนาเช่นไร
Yu'er,
อวี๋เอ๋อร์
I like you very much.
ข้าชอบเจ้าจริง ๆ
I can't bear to see you die because of Qi Yan.
ไม่อาจทนดูเจ้าไปตายเปล่าเพื่อฉีเยี่ยน
Listen to me and leave Heng'an City.
เชื่อข้านะ ไปจากเหิงอัน
You should leave the Xing empire.
ไปจากต้าซิง
You can go anywhere else.
ไปที่ไหนก็ได้
Never return here
ชีวิตนี้ชาตินี้
for the rest of your life.
ไม่ต้องกลับมาอีก
Yanzhi!
เยียนจือ
Please stop.
ท่านวางมือเถอะ
If you kill the current emperor
หากท่านฆ่าฮ่องเต้
and replace him with another emperor,
แล้วยกฮ่องเต้ใหม่ขึ้นมา
you'll be the same
เช่นนั้นท่านจะต่างอะไรกับ
as Qiu Ziliang!
ฉิวจื่อเหลียงล่ะ
Xiu,
อาซิว
take her away.
คุมตัวนางไป
Send four troops
ส่งทหารเบี้ยสี่นาย
to escort her out of the pass.
ส่งนางออกจากด่านด้วยตัวเอง
Understood.
ได้
Someone.
ทหาร
Yanzhi,
เยียนจือ
just kill me then.
เช่นนั้นก็ฆ่าข้าเสีย
How could I be a Sword Bearer
หากให้ข้ามีชีวิตรอดไปวัน ๆ
if I have to escape by myself like a coward?
จะเป็นผู้ถือกระบี่ประสาอะไร
Yanzhi!
เยียนจือ
Qi Yan,
ฉีเยี่ยน
how are you fortunate enough
เจ้ามีดีอย่างไร
to have her as your Sword Bearer?
จึงได้มีผู้ถือกระบี่เช่นนี้
Qiu Ziliang.
ฉิวจื่อเหลียง
Where's the Commander's Seal?
ตราอาญาสิทธิ์อยู่ที่ไหน
Will I be able to live
มอบตราอาญาสิทธิ์ให้
once I've given you the seal?
แล้วมีชีวิตรอดไหมเล่า
No.
ไม่มี
Why should I give it to you then?
เช่นนั้นไยข้าต้องมอบให้เจ้าด้วย
Yes, sir.
ขอรับ
How's the situation inside?
สถานการณ์ด้านในเป็นอย่างไร
Yanzhi said
เยียนจือบอกว่า
she's going to kill
จะฆ่าทั้งฝ่าบาท
both His Majesty and Qiu Ziliang.
และฉิวจื่อเหลียง
Let's hurry and save them.
พวกเรารีบเข้าไปช่วยพวกเขากัน
I'll bear all responsibilities.
มีเรื่องอะไรข้าแบกรับเอง
Let's go.
ไปเถอะ
Wait.
รอเดี๋ยว
Look at the state you're in.
เจ้าเป็นเช่นนี้แล้ว
And, Qiu Ziliang and Han Yue
อีกทั้งฉิวเยียนจือกับหานเยว่
have joined hands.
ร่วมมือกันแล้ว
Our powers alone won't be enough to defeat them.
ลำพังแค่กำลังของพวกเราไม่พอหรอก
What should we do then?
เช่นนั้นจะทำอย่างไรดี
Now, we can only take a leap of faith.
บัดนี้เราทำได้เพียงหยิบยืมกำลัง
What do you mean?
หมายความว่าอย่างไร
Qiu Ziliang was captured.
ฉิวจื่อเหลียงก็ถูกจับแล้ว
What do you think the eunuchs will do
ถ้าหากข่าวนี้ถูกแพร่ออกไป
when they hear of this?
กลุ่มขุนนางจะเป็นอย่างไร
Cheng Ruoyu, listen up.
เฉิงรั่วอวี๋ ข้าจะบอกเจ้าให้
It's late right now.
กลางดึกเช่นนี้
If you dare to deceive me,
ถ้าเจ้ากล้าหลอกข้า
I won't show you any mercy.
อย่าหาว่าข้าไม่เกรงใจนะ
Hurry!
เร็วเข้า
Ruoqing.
รั่วชิง
General Han, are you okay?
แม่ทัพหาน ท่านไม่เป็นอะไรใช่ไหม
I'm fine.
ข้าไม่เป็นอะไร
But Qi Yan is missing.
แต่ฉีเยี่ยนเขาหายตัวไปแล้ว
If,
ถ้าหาก
they didn't come out before the explosion,
พวกเขาไม่ออกมาก่อนระเบิด
that means everything is over.
เช่นนั้นทุกอย่างก็สิ้นสุดแล้ว
This is bad.
แย่แล้ว
I think the eunuchs are here.
กลุ่มขุนนางน่าจะมาแล้ว
General Han,
แม่ทัพหาน
you should retreat first.
ท่านถอยไปก่อน
No.
ไม่ได้
We must leave together.
ถ้าจะไป พวกเราไปด้วยกัน
They still have no idea
พวกเขายังไม่รู้
about my true identity.
ตัวตนที่แท้จริงของข้า
I'll stay here
ข้าอยู่ต่อ
and observe the situation.
คอยดูท่าทีสถานการณ์
Wait for my news.
ท่านรอข่าวจากข้า
Just go!
รีบไป
All right.
ได้
Hide this.
ซ่อนให้ดี
Where's Grandfather?
ท่านปู่เล่า
- He's inside? - His Majesty.
- อยู่ด้านในหรือ - ฝ่าบาท
His Majesty.
ฝ่าบาท
I'm talking to you!
ข้าถามเจ้าอยู่นะ
Commander Wang,
ผู้บัญชาการกองทัพหวัง
you are to respect the Chess Overseer!
ห้ามเสียมารยาทกับผู้นำสำนักหมากรุก
Nonsense!
ถุย
Listen up.
ข้าจะบอกพวกเจ้าให้
If anything happens to my grandfather,
หากท่านปู่เป็นอะไรไป
I'll hold you guys responsible for it!
ข้า ข้าจะเอาเรื่องกับเจ้าก่อน
Go and uncover the rubble!
ไปขุดสิ
Yes, sir!
ขอรับ
Hurry!
เร็วเข้า
Yanzhi.
เยียนจือ
Where's His Majesty?
ฝ่าบาทเล่า
- Yanzhi! - Where's His Majesty?
เยียนจือ ฝ่าบาทเล่า
I told you to leave,
ข้าให้เจ้าไปแล้ว
yet you've returned here
เจ้ายังจะ
time and time again.
กลับมาซ้ำแล้วซ้ำเล่า
I'm His Majesty's Sword Bearer.
ข้าคือผู้ถือกระบี่ของฝ่าบาท
I will live and die together with His Majesty!
สาบานร่วมเป็นร่วมตายกับฝ่าบาท
But you brought the Shencai Army here.
แต่เจ้าพาทัพเสินไฉมาด้วย
They're here to save Qiu Ziliang.
พวกเขามาช่วยฉิวจื่อเหลียงกันทั้งนั้น
I have no choice.
ตอนนี้ข้าไม่มีวิธีอื่นแล้ว
I need to save His Majesty.
ข้าเพียงจะช่วยฝ่าบาท
Cheng Ruoyu,
เฉิงรั่วอวี๋
my entire effort went down the drain
เจ้าทำลาย
all because of you.
สิ่งที่ข้าพยายามมาทั้งหมด
Yanzhi,
เยียนจือ
now, you should save His Majesty together with me.
ตอนนี้ท่านไปช่วยฝ่าบาทกับข้า
In the future, I'll surely
แล้วภายหลังข้าจะต้อง
join hands with you and deal with Qiu Ziliang,
ไปจัดการกับฉิวจื่อเหลียงกับท่านแน่
all right?
ได้หรือไม่
Qi Yan is dead.
ฉีเยี่ยนตายแล้ว
Qi Yan didn't come out
ก่อนระเบิด
before the explosion.
ฉีเยี่ยนไม่ได้ออกมา
That's impossible.
เป็นไปไม่ได้
Your Majesty!
ฝ่าบาท
Over here.
ทางนี้
Hurry! Search for him!
เร็วเข้า รีบตามหา
Dig this out! Hurry!
ขุด เร็วเข้า
Ask more men to help us out.
มาช่วยทางนี้หน่อย
Yes, sir.
ขอรับ
Come. Over there as well.
มา ตรงนั้นด้วย
Be careful.
ค่อย ๆ ค่อย ๆ
Lend me a hand.
มาช่วยหน่อย
- Lend me a hand. - All right.
มาช่วยข้าที
Help me out.
มาช่วยที
- We need two more men. - Coming.
- มาอีกสองคน - มาแล้ว ขอรับ
- On the count of three. - All right.
ไปด้วยกัน ๆ ไป
Over there.
ตรงนั้นด้วย
Be careful.
ค่อย ๆ
Take this.
รับหน่อย
Over here as well.
ตรงนี้ยังมีอีก
Come over here.
มาตรงนี้
- Over there. - Be careful.
มีตรงนี้อีก ระวัง
Be careful.
ค่อย ๆ ค่อย ๆ ค่อย ๆ
- Get us some water. - Yes, sir.
- ไปตักน้ำมาอีก - ขอรับ
Commander Wang,
ผู้บัญชาการกองทัพหวัง
the fire has been extinguished.
ไฟดับแล้ว
There are no signs of Official Qiu.
แต่ไม่เห็นเงาใต้เท้าเลยขอรับ
I think there's a secret chamber down there.
เหมือนใต้ดินจะมีกลไก
The fire was caused by ignited gunpowder.
สาเหตุของไฟไหม้คือดินปืนระเบิด
The ground collapsed because of it.
ทำให้พื้นทรุด
A secret chamber?
กลไกหรือ
Gunpowder?
ดินปืนหรือ
Do you have a map of the secret chamber?
มีแผนผังกลไกหรือไม่
Bring it to me!
เอามาสิ
It's inside the building.
อยู่ในห้อง
Now,
ตอนนี้
I'm afraid it has been turned into ashes.
เกรงจะสลายกลายเป็นเถ้าถ่านแล้ว
Useless fools!
พวกสวะ
Continue digging!
ขุดต่อไป
I need to see his body
อยู่ต้องเจอคน
even if he's dead!
ตายต้องเจอศพ
- Yes, Commander! - Hurry.
ใช่ เร็วเข้า
- Over here. - All right.
ทางนี้ ทางนี้ ได้
You guys, come over here!
คนทางนั้น มานี่ให้หมด
- Yes, sir!
ขอรับ ๆ
Over here.
ทางนี้
All right.
ได้
Someone!
ทหาร
Arrest her!
จับนางไว้
Commander Wang,
ผู้บัญชาการกองทัพหวัง
what do you mean by this?
ท่านหมายความว่าอย่างไร
I suspect that she has something to do with this incident!
ข้าสงสัยว่านางจะเกี่ยวข้องกับเรื่องนี้
What evidence do you have?
ท่านมีหลักฐานอะไร
It's obvious that Zhenwu's military advisor
เห็นชัด ๆ ว่าเรื่องนี้
is the mastermind behind this incident.
เป็นฝีมือของกุนซือเจิ้นอู๋
Commander Wang,
ผู้บัญชาการกองทัพหวัง
I don't know
ข้าไม่รู้ว่า
what Cheng Ruoyu had told you,
เฉิงรั่วอวี๋บอกอะไรกับท่าน
but, the Violet Bureau
แต่ตลอดมาหน่วยอาภรณ์ม่วง
has always been on bad terms with us.
ไม่ถูกกับพวกเรา
Please think twice
คำพูดของนาง
before you trust her.
ขอท่านพินิจให้ดี
Is that so?
เช่นนั้นหรือ
At this crucial moment,
เวลาสำคัญเช่นนี้
Father is trapped underground.
ท่านพ่อถูกขังไว้ใต้ดิน
As his subordinates, you and I
ข้าและท่านล้วนเป็นคนของเขาเหมือนกัน
should work together and try to save him.
ควรจะต้องร่วมมือกันช่วยคนออกมาก่อน
We shouldn't fight with each other.
อย่าแตกคอกันเอง
Everyone, did you hear her?
ทุกคนฟังให้ดี
She said she was Grandfather's subordinate.
นางบอกว่านางคือคนของท่านปู่
How dare you put yourself on the same level as me
เป็นแค่ของสั่งการดีแต่รูป
when you're just a wretch who depends on her good looks?
คู่ควรจะเสวนากับข้างั้นหรือ
Arrest her!
จับไว้
Commander Wang,
ผู้บัญชาการกองทัพหวัง
the Chess Bearer is Official Qiu's favourite daughter.
ผู้นำสำนักหมากรุกเป็นบุตรีที่ใต้เท้ารัก
You should know the consequences
ท่านปฏิบัติต่อนางเช่นนี้
if you treat her in this way.
ท่านคงรู้ผลลัพธ์ดีใช่หรือไม่
Listen,
ข้าจะบอกให้
if Grandfather is fine,
ถ้าหากท่านปู่ปลอดภัย
she can continue to be his precious daughter.
นางก็เป็นแก้วตาดวงใจต่อไปได้
But, if something happens to Grandfather...
แต่หากท่านปู่เป็นอะไรไป
Continue digging!
ขุด
Yes, Commander.
ขอรับ
Cheng Ruoyu.
เฉิงรั่วอวี๋
Han Ding?
หานติ้ง
Yanzhi said
เยียนจือบอกว่า
His Majesty was dead.
ฝ่าบาทสวรรคตแล้ว
Come.
มา
- Let's put our back into it. - Yes, sir.
- ทุกคนช่วยกัน - ได้
Hurry! Remove the rubble!
เร็ว รีบขุดออกมา
Commander Wang,
ผู้บัญชาการกองทัพหวัง
we found someone!
ขุดออกมาได้คนหนึ่งขอรับ
- Move everything to the side. - All right.
- ย้ายไปไว้ทางนั้นให้หมด - ได้
Who is it?
ใครหรือ
Commander Wang,
ผู้บัญชาการกองทัพหวัง
we found someone!
ขุดคนออกมาได้หนึ่งคน
Is it Grandfather?
ใช่ท่านปู่หรือไม่
Bring him out.
รีบหามออกมา
I think the body
เหมือนจะเป็น
belongs to one of the soldier.
ทหารเบี้ยคนหนึ่งของสำนักหมากรุกขอรับ
Continue.
ขุด
Continue digging!
ขุดต่อไป
Yes, Commander!
ขอรับ
With their pace,
ขุดต่อไปเช่นนี้
they will find his body sooner or later.
ช้าเร็วก็ต้องขุดเจอ
Everything will be worth it
ขอเพียงฉิวจื่อเหลียงตายแล้ว
as long as Qiu Ziliang is dead.
ทุกอย่างก็คุ้มค่า
What if he's still alive?
ถ้าหากไม่ตายล่ะ
If that's the case,
เช่นนั้น
I'll have to resign to my fate then.
คงเป็นลิขิตสวรรค์
There's another body over here!
ตรงนี้ยังมีอีกหนึ่งคน
Dig his body out!
ขุดคนนี้ออกมา
There's another body here.
ตรงนี้ยังมีอีกคน
We found another body!
ตรงนี้ก็พบอีกคนขอรับ
Who is it?
ใครกัน
It belongs to another soldier.
ยังคงเป็นทหารเบี้ยขอรับ
Be careful.
ระวังหน่อย
Will we be able to help Prince Guang ascend the throne
พวกเราทำให้กวงอ๋องขึ้นครองราชย์ได้
within four hours?
อย่างราบรื่นได้ภายในสองชั่วยามหรือไม่
That's impossible,
เป็นไปไม่ได้
am I right?
ใช่ไหม
But, at least we can confirm
แต่อย่างน้อยเราแน่ใจได้ว่า
whether Qiu Ziliang and Qi Yan
ฉีเยี่ยนกับฉิวจื่อเหลียง
are still alive or not.
ยังมีชีวิตอยู่หรือไม่
How do you plan to confirm that?
ท่านจะแน่ใจได้อย่างไร
Although the Eta Ursae Majoris exit has been destroyed,
แม้ทางออกตำแหน่งเหยากวงจะทลายลง
the Alpha Ursae Majoris exit is quite far away from it.
แต่ตำแหน่งเทียนซูอยู่ห่างไกล
I think it should be intact.
น่าจะปลอดภัย
You wish to investigate the situation by using the Alpha Ursae Majoris exit?
ท่านจะเข้าไปตรวจจากตำแหน่งเทียนซูหรือ
But, we have to hide this from everyone here.
แต่ต้องปกปิดทุกคนในที่นี้
What should we do?
ทำอย่างไร
Tell Wang Lin
เจ้าไปบอกหวังหลิน
that although the map was destroyed,
แม้ว่าแผนผังจะมลายไปแล้ว
there's a spare map
แต่ยังมีฉบับสำรอง
in the Left Minister's library.
อยู่ที่หอเก็บตำราของจั่วเซี่ยง
He'll only give the map to me
มีเพียงข้าต้องไปด้วยตนเอง
when I visit him personally.
เขาถึงจะยอมมอบให้ข้า
They'll be able to speed up the process with the map.
เมื่อมีแผนผังแล้วก็จะขุดได้เร็วขึ้น
I'll ask him to release me.
แล้วก็ให้เขาปล่อยข้าไป
What if Wang Lin tries to get the map from the Left Minister himself?
ถ้าเผื่อหวังหลินบีบบังคับเอาจากจั่วเซี่ยงเล่า
He doesn't dare to do it.
เขาไม่กล้าหรอก
Before the Left Minister's retirement,
ก่อนที่จั่วเซี่ยงจะปลดเกษียณ
he was one of the eunuchs as well.
ก็เป็นขุนนางเหมือนกัน
He still has some lingering authority.
ยังคงหลงเหลืออำนาจอยู่บ้าง
Commander Wang.
ผู้บัญชาการกองทัพหวัง
the Chess Bearer has something to discuss with you.
ผู้นำสำนักหมากรุกมีเรื่องสำคัญอยากหารือกับท่าน
I've passed your message to him.
บอกแล้วเรียบร้อย
You better don't try anything funny.
ห้ามมีลูกไม้ตุกติก
I'm just
ข้าเป็นเพียง
a weak woman who can't even defend myself.
ผู้หญิงอ่อนแอคนหนึ่ง
What can I do?
จะมีลูกไม้อะไรได้
You,
เจ้า
keep an eye
สองคนนะ
on them.
ดูไว้ให้ดี
Make haste.
รีบไปรีบกลับ
- Yes, Commander.
ขอรับ
What are you looking at?
มองอะไรหรือ
I just wonder
ข้าก็แค่อยากเห็นว่า
how your face will look like
เมื่อท่านเรียกข้าว่าแม่
when you have to call me Mother.
จะเป็นอย่างไรกันนะ
Don't worry,
ท่านวางใจเถอะ
when Father has returned,
รอท่านพ่อออกมาได้
I will ask him to command you to do so.
ข้าจะขอเขาให้ท่านทำเช่นนี้แน่
Farewell,
ไว้เจอกัน
Commander Wang.
ผู้บัญชาการกองทัพหวัง
♪Life is a dream, how long do happy times last♪
♪ชีวิตล่องลอยดุจฝัน เคยสุขกี่ครั้ง♪
♪The sword can't break this karma♪
♪ชักดาบฟันฟาด กลับมิอาจสะบั้นเหตุและผล♪
♪Look how blurry and lonely the world is♪
♪มองฟ้ามองดินล้วนไม่ยินไม่แยแส♪
♪Still can't let go of this life as time goes by♪
♪ตะวันรุ่งจันทราโรย ชีพนี้ยังคงน่าถนอม♪
♪Even the iron and golden dagger-axe cannot extinguish the fire in my heart♪
♪ควบอาชาพร้อมอาวุธ มิอาจหยุดไฟในทรวง♪
♪Remembering the past and letting time while away♪
♪คิดถึงฝันในวันเก่า นานเท่านาน ยังคงเจ็บ♪
♪The past is in front of you♪
♪อดีตพลันไหลผ่านสองตา♪
♪Forgetting while piecing it together♪
♪ทางหนึ่งเพียรลืม อีกทางเพียรจำ♪
♪Like when I sincerely put my hands together♪
♪หากข้าประกบมือประนมกร♪
♪I only wish that you can be saved♪
♪ไหว้วอนให้เจ้าได้หลุดพ้น♪
♪The past is in front of you♪
♪อดีตพลันไหลผ่านสองตา♪
♪Forgetting while piecing it together♪
♪ทางหนึ่งเพียรลืม อีกทางเพียรจำ♪
♪Like when I sincerely put my hands together♪
♪หากข้าประกบมือประนมกร♪
♪I only wish that you can be saved♪
♪ไหว้วอนให้เจ้าได้หลุดพ้น♪